In this second tutorial video on
在第二段关于 Octave的
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
Octave, I'd like to start
辅导课视频中 我将开始介绍
to tell you how to move data around in Octave.
如何在 Octave 中移动数据
So, if you have data for
具体来说
a machine learning problem, how do you load that data in Octave?
如果你有一个机器学习问题 你怎样把数据加载到 Octave 中？
How do you put it into matrix?
怎样把数据存入一个矩阵？
How do you manipulate these matrices?
如何对矩阵进行相乘？
How do you save the results?
如何保存计算结果？
How do you move data around and operate with data?
如何移动这些数据 并用数据进行操作？
Here's my Octave window as
和之前一样 这是我的 Octave 窗口
before, picking up from where we left off in the last video.
我们继续沿用上次的窗口
If I type A, that's
我键入 A
the matrix so we generate it, right,
得到我们之前构建的矩阵 A
with this command equals one, two,
也就是用这个命令生成的
three, four, five, six, and
A = [1 2; 3 4; 5 6]
this is a three by two matrix.
这是一个三行二列的矩阵
The size command in Octave
Octave 中的 size() 命令
lets you, tells you what is the size of a matrix.
返回矩阵的尺寸
So size A returns three, two.
所以 size(A) 命令返回3 2
It turns out that
实际上
this size command itself is actually
size() 命令返回的
returning a one by two matrix.
是一个 1×2 的矩阵
So you can actually set SZ equals
我们可以用 sz 来存放
size of A and SZ
设置 sz = size(A)
is now a one by two
因此 sz 就是一个1×2的矩阵
matrix where the first element
第一个元素是3
of this is three, and the second element of this is two.
第二个元素是2
So, if you just type size of SZ. Does SZ
所以如果键入 size(sz) 看看 sz 的尺寸
is a one by
返回的是1 2
two matrix whose two elements
表示是一个1×2的矩阵
contain the dimensions of the
1 和 2 分别表示
matrix A. You can
矩阵 A 的维度 (此处口误 应为 sz 的维度 译者注)
also type size A one
你也可以键入 size(A, 1)
to give you back the first
这个命令会返回
dimension of A, size
A 矩阵的第一个元素
of the first dimension of A.
A 矩阵的第一个维度的尺寸
So that's the number
也就是 A 矩阵的行数
of rows and size A two
同样 命令 size(A, 2)
to give you back two, which
将返回2
is the number of columns in
也就是 A 矩阵的列数
the matrix A.  If you
have a vector V, so
如果你有一个向量 v
let's say V equals one, two,
假如 v = [1 2 3 4]
three, four, and you
type length V.  What
然后键入 length(v)
this does is it gives you
这个命令将返回
the size of the longest dimension.
最大维度的大小
So you can also type
你也可以键入 length(A)
length A and because
由于矩阵 A
A is a three by
是一个3×2的矩阵
two matrix, the longer
因此最大的维度
dimension is of size
应该是3
three, so this should print out three.
因此该命令会返回3
But usually we apply length only to vectors.
但通常我们还是对向量使用 length 命令
So you know, length one, two,
比如 length([1;2;3;4;5])
three, four, five, rather
than apply length to matrices
而不是对矩阵使用 length 命令
because that's a little more confusing.
因为毕竟有点容易让人弄混
Now, let's look
下面让我们来看看
at how the load data and
如何在系统中
find data on the file system.
加载数据和寻找数据
When we start an Octave
当我们打开 Octave 时
we're usually, we're often in
我们通常已经在一个
a path that
默认路径中
is, you know, the location of where the Octave location is.
这个路径是 Octave 的安装位置
So the PWD command shows
pwd 命令可以显示出
the current directory, or the
Octave 当前所处路径
current path that Octave is in.
So right now we're in this maybe somewhat off scale directory.
所以现在我们就在这个目录下
The CD command stands
cd 命令
for change directory, so I
意思是改变路径
can go to C:/Users/Ang/Desktop, and
我可以把路径改为C:\Users\ang\Desktop
now I'm in, you know, in my Desktop
这样当前目录就变为了桌面
and if I type ls,
如果键入 ls
ls is, it comes from a Unix or a Linux command.
ls 来自于一个 Unix 或者 Linux 命令
But, ls will list the
ls 命令将列出
directories on my desktop and
我桌面上的所有路径
so these are the files
因此这些就是
that are on my Desktop right now.
我桌面上的所有文件了
In fact, on my desktop are
事实上 我的桌面上
two files: Features X and
有两个文件
Price Y that's maybe come
featuresX.dat 和 priceY.dat
from a machine learning problem I want to solve.
是两个我想解决的机器学习问题
So, here's my desktop.
这是我的桌面
Here's Features X, and
这是 featuresX 文件
Features X is this window,
featuresX 文件如这个窗口所示
excuse me, is this file with two columns of data.
是一个含有两列数据的文件
This is actually my housing prices data.
这其实就是我的房屋价格数据
So I think, you know, I
我想应该是
think I have forty-seven rows in this data set.
数据集中有47行
And so the first house
第一个房子样本
has size two hundred four
面积是2104平方英尺
square feet, has three bedrooms; second
有3个卧室
house has sixteen hundred square
第二套房子面积为1600
feet, has three bedrooms; and so on.
有3个卧室 等等
And Price Y is this
priceY 是这个文件
file that has
也就是
the prices of the data in my training set.
训练集中的价格数据
So, Features X and
所以 featuresX 和
Price Y are just text files with my data.
priceY 就是两个存放数据的文档
How do I load this data into Octave?
那么应该怎样把数据读入 Octave 呢？
Well, I just type
好的 我们只需要键
the command load Features X dot
键入 featuresX.dat
dat and if I
这样
do that, I load the Features X
我将加载了 featuresX 文件
and can load Price Y dot dat. And
同样地我可以加载 priceY.dat
by the way, there are multiple ways to do this.
其实有好多种办法可以完成
This command if you put
如果你把命令写成
Features X dot dat on that
字符串的形式 load('featureX.dat')
in strings and load it like so.
也是可以的
This is a typo there.
这里打错了
This is an equivalent command.
这跟刚才的命令效果是相同的
So you can, this
只不过是把文件名
way I'm just putting the file name of the string
写成了一个字符串的形式
in the founding in a
现在文件名被存在一个
string and in an
字符串中
Octave use single quotes to
Octave 中使用引号
represent strings, like so.
来表示字符串 就像这样
So that's a string, and we
这就是一个字符串
can load the file
因此我们读取的文件
whose name is given by that string.
文件名由这个字符串给出
Now the WHO command now
另外 who 命令
shows me what variables I
能显示出 在我的 Octave
have in my Octave workspace.
工作空间中的所有变量
So Who shows me whether
因此 who 命令显示出
the variables that Octave has in memory currently.
当前 Octave 储存的变量
Features X and Price Y
包括 featureX 和 priceY
are among them, as well as
同样还包括
the variables that, you know,
在此之前你创建的
we created earlier in this session.
那些变量
So I can type Features X
所以我可以键入
to display features X. And
featuresX 回车 来显示 featuresX
there's my data.
这些就是存在里面的数据
And I can type size features
还可以键入 size(featuresX)
X and that's my
得出的结果是 47 2
47 by two matrix.
代表这是一个47×2的矩阵
And some of these size, press
类似地
Y, that gives me
输入 size(priceY)
my 47 by one vector.
结果是 47 1
This is a 47 dimensional vector.
表示这是一个47维的向量
This is all common vector that
是一个列矩阵
has all the prices Y in my training set.
存放的是训练集中的所有价格 Y 的值
Now the who function shows
who 函数能让你看到
you one of the variables that, in the current workspace.
当前工作空间中的所有变量
There's also the who S
同样还有另一个 whos 命令
variable that gives you the detailed view.
能更详细地进行查看
And so this also, with
因此
an S at the end this also
在 who 后面加一个 s
lists my variables except that it
同样也列出我所有的变量
now lists the sizes as well.
不仅如此 还列出了变量的维度
So A is a three by
我们看到 A 是一个
two matrix and features
3×2的矩阵
X as a 47 by 2 matrix.
X 是一个47×2的矩阵
Price Y is a 47 by one matrix.
priceY 是一个47×1的矩阵
Meaning this is just a vector.
也就是一个向量
And it shows, you know, how many bytes of memory it's taking up.
同时还显示出 需要占用多少内存空间
As well as what type of data this is.
以及数据类型是什么
Double means double position floating
double 意思是双精度浮点型
point so that just means that
这也就是说
these are real values, the floating point numbers.
这些数都是实数 是浮点数
Now if you want to get
如果你想删除某个变量
rid of a variable you can use the clear command.
你可以使用 clear 命令
So clear features X and type whose again.
因此 我们键入 clear featuresX
You notice that the features X
然后再输入 whos 命令
variable has now disappeared.
你会发现 featuresX 消失了
And how do we save data?
另外 我们怎么储存数据呢？
Let's see.
我们来看
Let's take the variable V and
我们设变量 v
say that it's a price Y 1 colon 10.
为 priceY(1:10)
This sets V to be
这表示的是将向量 Y 的
the first 10 elements of
前10个元素存入 v 中
vector Y. So let's type who or whose.
我们输入 who 或者 whos
Whereas Y was a 47 by 1 vector.
Y 是一个47×1的向量
V is now 10 by 1.
因此现在 v 就是10×1的向量
B equals price Y, one
因为刚才设置了
column ten that sets it
v = priceY(1:10)
to the just the first ten
这便将 v 的值
elements of Y. Let's say
设为了 Y 的前十个元素
I wanna save this to date to disc
假如我们想把它存入硬盘
the command save, hello.mat
那么用 save hello.mat v 命令
V. This will
这个命令
save the variable V into
会将变量 v
a file called hello.mat.
存成一个叫 hello.mat 的文件
So let's do that.
让我们回车
And now a file
现在我的桌面上
has appeared on my Desktop, you
就出现了一个新文件
know, called Hello.mat.
名为 hello.mat
I happen to have MATLAB installed
由于我的电脑里
in this window, which is why,
也同时安装了 MATLAB
you know, this icon looks
所以这个图标
like this because Windows is recognized
上面有 MATLAB 的标识
as it's a MATLAB file,but don't
因为操作系统把文件识别为 MATLAB 文件
worry about it if this file
所以如果在你的电脑上
looks like it has a different
图标显示的不一样的话
icon on your machine and
也没有关系
let's say I clear all my variables.
现在我们清除所有变量
So, if you type clear without
直接键入 clear
anything then this actually deletes all of the variables in your workspace.
这样将删除工作空间中的所有变量
So there's now nothing left in the workspace.
所以现在工作空间中啥都没了
And if I load hello.mat,
但如果我载入 hello.mat 文件
I can now load back my
我又重新读取了变量 v
variable v, which is
因为我之前
the data that I
把变量 v存入了
previously saved into the hello.mat file.
hello.mat 文件中
So, hello.mat, what we did just now to save hello.mat
所以我们刚才用 save 命令做了什么
to view, this save the
这个命令把数据
data in a binary format,
按照二进制形式储存
a somewhat more compressed binary format.
或者说是更压缩的二进制形式
So if v is a lot
因此 如果 v 是很大的数据
of data, this, you know, will be somewhat more compressing.
那么压缩幅度也更大
Will take off less the space.
占用空间也更小
If you want to save your
如果你想把数据
data in a human readable
存成一个人能看懂的形式
format then you type save hello.text
那么可以键入
the variable v and then -ascii.
save hello.txt v -ascii
So, this will save
这样就会把数据
it as a text
存成一个文本文档
or as ascii format of text.
或者将数据的 ascii 码存成文本文档
And now, once I've done
现在 我键入了这个命令以后
that, I have this file.
我的桌面上
Hello.text has just
就有了 hello.txt 文件
appeared on my desktop, and
if I open this up, we
如果打开它
see that this is a text
我们可以发现
file with my data saved away.
这个文本文档存放着我们的数据
So that's how you load and save data.
这就是读取和储存数据的方法
Now let's talk a bit about how to manipulate data.
接下来我们再来讲讲操作数据的方法
Let's set a equals to that
假如 A 还是那个矩阵
matrix again so is my three by two matrix.
跟刚才一样还是那个 3×2 的矩阵
So as indexing.
现在我们加上索引值
So type A 3, 2.
比如键入 A(3,2)
This indexes into
这将索引到
the 3, 2 elements of
A 矩阵的 (3,2) 元素
the matrix A. So, this
is what, you know,
这就是我们通常
in normally, we will write this
书写矩阵的形式
as a subscript 3, 2
写成 A 下标32
or A subscript,
下标32
you know, 3, 2
3和2分别表示
and so that's the element and
矩阵的第三行
third row and second column
和第二列对应的元素
of A which is the element of six.
因此也就对应 6
I can also type A to
我也可以键入
comma colon to fetch
A(2,:) 来返回
everything in the second row.
第二列的所有元素
So, the colon means every
因此 冒号表示
element along that row or column.
该行或该列的所有元素
So, a of 2 comma
因此 A(2,:)
colon is this second row of a. Right.
表示 A 矩阵的第二行的所有元素
And similarly, if I do a colon comma 2
类似地 如果我键入 A(:,2)
then this means get everything in
这将返回 A 矩阵第二列的所有元素
the second column of A. So, this gives me 2 4 6.
这将得到 2 4 6
Right this means of
这表示返回
A.  everything, second column.
A 矩阵的第二列的所有元素
So, this is my second
因此这就是
column A, which is 2 4 6.
矩阵 A 的第二列 就是 2 4 6
Now, you can also
你也可以在运算中
use somewhat most of the sophisticated index in the operations.
使用这些较为复杂的索引
So So, we just click each of an example.
我再给你展示几个例子
You do this maybe less often,
可能你也不会经常使用
but let me do this A 1 3 comma colon.
但我还是输入给你看 A([1 3],:)
This means get all of
这个命令意思是
the elements of A who's first indexes one or three.
取 A 矩阵第一个索引值为1或3的元素
This means I get everything from
也就是说我取的是
the first and third rows of
A 矩阵的第一行和
A and from all
第三行的每一列
columns.
So, this was the
这是 A 矩阵
matrix A and so A
因此
1 3 comma colon means get
输入 A([1 3], :)
everything from the first row
返回第一行
and from the second row and
返回第三行
from the third row and the
冒号表示的是
colon means, you know, one both
取这两行的每一列元素
of first and the second
也就是第一行
columns and so this
和第二行的所有元素(此处口误 应为第三行 译者注)
gives me this 1 2 5 6.
因此返回结果为 1 2 5 6
Although, you use the source
可能这些比较复杂一点的
of more subscript index
索引操作
operations maybe somewhat less often.
你不会经常用到
To show you what else we can do.
我们还能做什么呢
Here's the A matrix and this
这依然是 A 矩阵
source A colon, to give me the second column.
A(:,2) 命令返回第二列
You can also use this to do assignments.
你也可以为它赋值
So I can take the second column of
所以我可以取 A 矩阵的第二列
A and assign that to
然后将它赋值为
10, 11, 12, and
10 11 12
if I do that I'm now, you
如果我这样做的话
know, taking the second column of
我实际上是取出了 A 的第二列
a and I'm assigning this column vector 10, 11, 12 to it.
然后把一个列向量[10;11;12]赋给了它
So, now a is this matrix that's 1, 3, 5.
因此现在 A 矩阵的第一列还是 1 3 5
And the second column has been replaced by 10, 11, 12.
第二列就被替换为 10 11 12
And here's another operation.
接下来一个操作
Let's set A to be equal
让我们把 A 设为
to A comma 100, 101,
A = [A, [100, 101, 102]]
102 like so and what
这样做的结果是
this will do is
在原矩阵的右边
depend another column vector
附加了一个新的列矩阵
to the right.
So, now, oops.
现在 见证奇迹的时刻...
I think I made a little mistake.
噢 我又犯错了
Should have put semicolons there
应该放分号的
and now A is equals to this.
现在 A 矩阵就是这样了
Okay?
对吧？
I hope that makes sense.
我希望你听懂了
So this 100, 101, 102.
所以 [100;101;102]
This is a column vector
这是个列矩阵
and what we did
而我们所做的
was we set A, take
就是把 A 矩阵设置为
A and set it to the original definition.
原来的 A 矩阵
And then we put that column
再在右边附上一个
vector to the right
新添加的列矩阵
and so, we ended up taking
我们的原矩阵 A
the matrix A and--which was
就是右边这个6个元素
these six elements on the left.
So we took matrix
所以我们就是把 A 矩阵
A and we appended another
右边加上了一个
column vector to the right;
新的列向量
which is now why A is
所以现在 A 矩阵
a three by three matrix that looks like that.
变成这样一个 3×3 的矩阵
And finally, one neat
最后 还有一个小技巧
trick that I sometimes use
我也经常使用
if you do just a and just a colon like so.
如果你就输入 A(:)
This is a somewhat special case syntax.
这是一个很特别的语法结构
What this means is that put all elements with A into
意思是把 A 中的所有元素
a single column vector
放入一个单独的列向量
and this gives me a 9 by 1 vector.
这样我们就得到了一个 9×1 的向量
They adjust the other ones are combined together.
这些元素都是 A 中的元素排列起来的
Just a couple more examples. Let's see. Let's
再来几个例子好了
say I set A to be equal to 123456, okay?
我还是把 A 重新设为 [1 2; 3 4; 5 6]
And let's say
假如说
I set a B to B
我再设一个 B
equal to 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
为[11 12; 13 14; 15 16]
I can create a new
我可以新建一个矩阵 C
matrix C as A B.
C = [A B]
This just means my
这个意思就是
Matrix A. Here's my Matrix
这是我的矩阵 A
B and I've set C
这是我的矩阵 B
to be equal to AB.
我设 C = [A B]
What I'm doing is I'm taking
这样做的结果就是
these two matrices and just concatenating onto each other.
把这两个矩阵直接连在一起
So the left, matrix A on the left.
矩阵 A 在左边
And I have the matrix B on the right.
矩阵 B 在右边
And that's how I formed
这样组成了 C 矩阵
this matrix C by putting them together.
就是直接把 A 和 B 合起来
I can also do C equals
我还可以设
A semicolon B. The semi
C = [A; B]
colon notation means that
这里的分号表示
I go put the next thing at the bottom.
把分号后面的东西放到下面
So, I'll do is a
所以
equals semicolon B. It also
[A; B]的作用
puts the matrices A
依然还是把两个矩阵
and B together except that it
放在一起
now puts them on top of each other.
只不过现在是上下排列
so now I have A on top and B at the bottom and C here
所以现在 A 在上面 B 在下面
is now in 6 by 2 matrix.
C 就是一个 6×2 矩阵
So, just say the semicolon
简单地说
thing usually means, you know, go to the next line.
分号的意思就是换到下一行
So, C is comprised by a
所以 C 就包括上面的 A
and then go to the bottom
然后换行到下面
of that and then put b
然后在下面放上一个 B
in the bottom and by the
另外顺便说一下
way, this A B is
这个[A B]命令
the same as A, B and
跟 [A, B] 是一样的
so you know, either of these gives you the same result.
这两种写法的结果是相同的
So, with that, hopefully you
好了 通过以上这些操作
now know how to construct
希望你现在掌握了
matrices and hopefully starts
怎样构建矩阵
to show you some of the
也希望我展示的这些命令
commands that you use
能让你很快地学会
to quickly put together matrices and
怎样把矩阵放到一起
take matrices and, you know,
怎样取出矩阵
slam them together to form
并且把它们放到一起
bigger matrices, and with
组成更大的矩阵
just a few lines of code, Octave
通过几句简单的代码
is very convenient in terms
Octave 能够很方便地
of how quickly we can assemble
很快速地帮助我们
complex matrices and move data around.
组合复杂的矩阵以及对数据进行移动
So that's it for moving data around.
这就是移动数据这一节课
In the next video we'll start
在下一段视频中
to talk about how to actually
我们将一起来谈谈
do complex computations on this, on our data.
怎样利用数据进行更为复杂的计算
So, hopefully that gives you
希望这节课的内容
a sense of how, with
能让你明白
just a few commands, you can
在 Octave 中 怎样用几句简单的命令
very quickly move data around in Octave.
很快地对数据进行移动
You know, you load and save vectors and
包括加载和储存一个向量
matrices, load and save data,
或矩阵 加载和存储数据
put together matrices to create
把矩阵放在一起
bigger matrices, index into or select
构建更大的矩阵
specific elements on the matrices.
用索引对矩阵某个特定元素进行操作等等
I know I went through a lot
我知道可能我一下子
of commands, so I think
讲了很多命令
the best thing for you to do
所以我认为对你来讲
is afterward, to look
最好的学习方法是
at the transcript of the things I was typing.
下课后复习一下我键入的这些代码
You know, look at it.
好好地看一看
Look at the coursework site and download
从课程的网上
the transcript of the session
把代码的副本下载下来
from there and look through
重新好好看看这些副本
the transcript and type some
然后自己在 Octave 中
of those commands into Octave yourself
把这些命令重新输一遍
and start to play with these commands and get it to work.
慢慢开始学会使用这些命令
And obviously, you know, there's no point at all to try to memorize all these commands.
当然 没有必要把这些命令都记住
It's just, but what you
你也不可能记得住
should do is, hopefully from
你要做的就是
this video you have gotten a
从这段视频里
sense of the sorts of things you can do.
了解一下你可以用哪些命令 做哪些事
So that when later on when
这样在你今后需要
you are trying to program a learning
编写学习算法时
algorithms yourself, if you
如果你要找到某个
are trying to find a specific
Octave 中的命令
command that maybe you think
你可能回想起
Octave can do because you think
你之前在这里学到过
you might have seen it here, you
然后你就可以查找
should refer to the transcript
课程中提供的程序副本
of the session and look through
这样就能很轻松地找到
that in order to find the commands you wanna use.
你想使用的命令了
So, that's it for
好了 这就是
moving data around and in
移动数据这节课的全部内容
the next video what I'd like
在下一段视频中
to do is start to tell
我将开始向你介绍
you how to actually do
怎样进行一些
complex computations on our
更复杂的计算
data, and how to
怎样对数据进行计算
compute on the data, and
actually start to implement learning algorithms.
同时开始实现学习算法